<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>书评 on 1sle</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E4%B9%A6%E8%AF%84/</link>
        <description>Recent content in 书评 on 1sle</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>1sle</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E4%B9%A6%E8%AF%84/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>书评/ 昨日的世界</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-world-of-yesterday/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-world-of-yesterday/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;斯特凡•茨威格 (Stefan Zweig)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;茨威格笔下的巴黎第一次让我对这座城市心生向往。在他眼中，战前的巴黎（乃至整个欧洲）宛如一座闪耀着理想主义光辉的乌托邦。塞纳河畔，自由的种子破土而出，平等的旗帜在伟人们的呐喊中高高飘扬。那是一个青春永驻的时代：街巷里回荡着欢乐的旋律，屋檐下孕育着无限的可能性。这个巴黎不再只是文学中的象征，而是一座承载人类最纯粹理想的精神花园，每个人都能在自由与平等的晨曦中找到自己的位置。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然而，象征着人类理想的城市终究未能逃脱时代的洪流。从战前的繁荣到两次世界大战后的毁灭，茨威格以亲身经历见证了理想主义的破灭与人性的幽暗。他告诉我们，了解一座城市、一个国家，乃至一个民族，仅仅靠书本与匆匆游览是远远不够的，真正的理解需要与其人民建立深厚的情感联结。个体的命运常常被时代的风暴裹挟，历史的齿轮一次次碾碎美好的希望： 在极权政治的阴影下，理想破灭者服毒自尽，狡诈之徒趁乱攫取荣华，而剩下的芸芸众生在命运长河中随波逐流，苟且偷生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;整部作品闪耀着深刻的人文关怀，不仅记录了历史，更深刻反思了人类的命运。尽管茨威格的视角是少数的、精英的、幸运的，但他对人性本质的洞察与对和平的呼吁却具有普遍意义 人类文化的建构能否压制内心的原始性，抑或这只是另一个历史循环的起点？ 只是当所有美好的记忆被摧毁、金色的时光化为灰烬时，自我毁灭也未免不是一种保存理想的抗争方式。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zweig&amp;rsquo;s Paris was the first to make me yearn for this city. In his eyes, pre-war Paris (and indeed all of Europe) was like a utopia shining with the light of idealism. Along the Seine, seeds of freedom sprouted, and flags of equality flew high amid the calls of great figures. It was an age of eternal youth: joyful melodies echoed through the streets, and endless possibilities grew under the eaves. This Paris was no longer just a symbol in literature, but a spiritual garden carrying humanity&amp;rsquo;s purest ideals, where everyone could find their place in the dawn of freedom and equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this city symbolizing human ideals could not escape the torrents of time. From pre-war prosperity to destruction after two world wars, Zweig personally witnessed the collapse of idealism and the darkness of human nature. He tells us that understanding a city, a country, or even a nation cannot be achieved merely through books and hasty tours; true understanding requires deep emotional connections with its people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual destinies are often swept up in the storms of their times, with history&amp;rsquo;s gears repeatedly crushing beautiful hopes: under the shadow of totalitarian politics, idealists took their own lives by poison, the cunning seized glory amid chaos, and the remaining masses drifted along the river of fate, barely surviving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire work shines with profound humanistic care, not only recording history but deeply reflecting on human destiny. Although Zweig&amp;rsquo;s perspective was that of a privileged minority elite, his insights into human nature and calls for peace hold universal significance. Can human cultural constructs suppress our primitive inner nature, or is this just the beginning of another historical cycle? Perhaps when all beautiful memories are destroyed and golden times turn to ashes, self-destruction becomes a form of resistance to preserve ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>书评/ 暗处的女儿</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/test-chinese/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/test-chinese/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;埃莱娜·费兰特通过一场沙滩上的偶遇，探讨了女性在母职与自我实现之间是否真的可以找到微妙的平衡点。她精准地描绘了母女关系中复杂而深刻的情感纽带——既有深沉的爱，也有难以启齿的恨；既有本能的疼惜，也有隐秘的控制欲；既有无私的奉献，也有难以抑制的嫉妒与竞争。这种情感交织，是任何男性作家都难以真实捕捉的独特体验。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自我的议题贯穿每个人生命始终，但与母亲的关系何尝不是同样难以逃离的命题？作品中的主人公面临着一个永恒的困境：在传统母职期待与个人自我实现之间，是否真的只能二选一？ 那些因自我意识强烈而逃离家庭的母亲究竟是懦弱，还是在进行勇敢的抗争？ 传统母职叙事用罗网将母亲塑造成无私奉献的圣人，仿佛在成为母亲的那一刻，就必须与过往的不成熟彻底切割，可是她们真的准备好了吗？ 母亲首先是人，是有自我意识和个人渴望的完整个体，而不是某种被理想化的工具。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;费兰特的笔触如同一把手术刀，细腻而精准地剖开了母亲的心理世界，揭示了母女之间那种既紧密相连又暗藏裂隙的关系。剖开后流出的，是血、是眼泪，是黑水、是周而复始的回响、是潜藏的渴望、不甘与无法言说的阴暗。母爱背面是挣扎、失落和渴望，而暗处的女儿们，则在母亲的阴影中成长，继承着她们的特质，在生命的长河中延续着这场永恒的循环。 她们或重复，或抗拒，或超越母亲的命运，但无论如何，但母女之间深刻的情感纽带始终像一根无形的丝线，将她们的生命编织在一起。这种深沉而复杂的联结，既是负累，也是力量。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a chance encounter on the beach, Elena Ferrante explores whether women can truly find a delicate balance between motherhood and self-realization. She precisely portrays the complex and profound emotional bonds in mother-daughter relationships - deep love alongside unspoken hatred; instinctive tenderness with hidden desires for control; selfless devotion mixed with uncontrollable jealousy and competition. This emotional interweaving represents a unique experience that male writers find difficult to capture authentically.
The question of self runs throughout everyone’s life, but isn’t the relationship with one’s mother equally inescapable? The protagonist faces an eternal dilemma: between traditional maternal expectations and personal self-realization, must it really be an either-or choice? Are mothers who flee their families due to strong self-awareness cowardly, or are they engaging in brave resistance? Traditional maternal narratives cast mothers as selfless saints with their web of expectations, as if the moment of becoming a mother requires a complete break from past immaturity - but are they truly ready?
A mother is first and foremost a human being, a complete individual with self-awareness and personal desires, not some idealized tool. Ferrante’s writing is like a surgical knife, delicately and precisely cutting open the psychological world of mothers, revealing the relationship between mothers and daughters that is both intimately connected yet harboring cracks. What flows out after the incision is blood, tears, dark water, recurring echoes, hidden desires, resentment, and unspeakable darkness.
Behind maternal love lies struggle, loss, and yearning, while in the shadows, daughters grow in their mothers’ shade, inheriting their characteristics, perpetuating this eternal cycle in the river of life. They may repeat, resist, or transcend their mothers’ fate, but regardless, the profound emotional bond between mother and daughter remains like an invisible thread, weaving their lives together. This deep and complex connection is both a burden and a source of strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
