<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>英国 on 1sle</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E8%8B%B1%E5%9B%BD/</link>
        <description>Recent content in 英国 on 1sle</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>1sle</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E8%8B%B1%E5%9B%BD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>书评/ 德伯家的苔丝</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-tess/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-tess/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;相关信息&#34;&gt;相关信息
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;托马斯·哈代  (Thomas Hardy）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;译者: 张谷若&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;出版社: 理想国&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;很喜欢哈代细腻又悲悯的描写。苔丝的悲剧，是一个美丽却贫穷的女人被迫承受家庭、社会和宗教多重压迫的缩影。她出生于一个好吃懒做、胸无大志却幻想通过嫁女儿改变命运的家庭。在19世纪的社会语境中，家庭负担、社会规训、宗教苛责，都是桎梏一个女人，尤其是一个受到侵害的女人的巨大枷锁。苔丝因所遭受的创伤而抬不起头，因为不够“纯洁”而被爱人遗弃，最终被命运再次推向自己的加害者。这样的命运悲剧怎么能归咎到苔丝身上呢？当苔丝终于奋起反抗、杀死罪人时，这一私刑式的报复却换来了众人的围剿与死刑的惩罚。所谓的道德原则成为了压死苔丝的判决书，这种伪善的道德所带来的系统性的压迫，不仅是苔丝们身上最沉重的镣铐，也是时代的原罪。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;刻画女性友情时，哈代也同样展现了细腻而温柔的笔触。在苔丝和另外三位女伴同时爱上克莱之后，她们的相处并未充满嫉妒与争夺，而是温和、克制又和谐。 至于克莱，他被哈代刻画为“本来有先进的思想、善良的用意，是最近二十五年以来这个时代里出产的典型人物。但虽然他极力想要以独立的见解判断事物，一旦事出非常，他不知不觉地还是信从小的时候所受的训教，还是成见习俗的奴隶。”克莱的挣扎与妥协，正是我们每个人的缩影：我们总以为自己拥有独立的思想，却依然常常不自觉地受制于成见和传统的枷锁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really appreciate Hardy’s delicate yet compassionate portrayal. Tess’s tragedy is a microcosm of a beautiful yet impoverished woman forced to endure the multiple oppressions of family, society, and religion. She was born into a family that is lazy, ambitionless, yet harbors the illusion of changing their fate by marrying off their daughter. In the social context of the 19th century, the burdens of family, the discipline of society, and the harsh judgment of religion all became enormous shackles restraining a woman—especially one who had been violated. Tess is weighed down by the trauma she suffered, abandoned by her lover for not being “pure” enough, and ultimately pushed back into the hands of her perpetrator by fate. How could such a tragic destiny ever be blamed on Tess herself? When she finally rises in resistance and kills her oppressor, her act of vigilante justice is met with public condemnation and the punishment of execution. The so-called moral principles become the verdict that crushes her. This hypocritical morality, bringing systemic oppression, is not only the heaviest chain shackling women like Tess but also the original sin of the era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardy’s delicate and gentle touch is also evident in his portrayal of female friendship. When Tess and her three companions fall in love with Angel, their interactions are not filled with jealousy or rivalry, but rather with restraint, harmony, and mutual understanding. As for Angel, Hardy portrays him as “a man of progressive thought and kind intentions, a typical product of the last twenty-five years. However, though he strives to judge things with independent insight, when faced with extraordinary circumstances, he unconsciously falls back on the teachings of his childhood and remains a slave to conventional prejudices.” Angel’s struggles and compromises are a reflection of us all: we often believe we possess independent thinking, yet unknowingly remain bound by preconceived notions and the chains of tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
