<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>2025 on 1sle</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/categories/2025/</link>
        <description>Recent content in 2025 on 1sle</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>1sle</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1sle29.github.io/categories/2025/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>书评/ 德伯家的苔丝</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-tess/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-tess/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;相关信息&#34;&gt;相关信息
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;托马斯·哈代  (Thomas Hardy）
译者: 张谷若
出版社: 理想国&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;很喜欢哈代细腻又悲悯的描写。苔丝的悲剧，是一个美丽却贫穷的女人被迫承受家庭、社会和宗教多重压迫的缩影。她出生于一个好吃懒做、胸无大志却幻想通过嫁女儿改变命运的家庭。在19世纪的社会语境中，家庭负担、社会规训、宗教苛责，都是桎梏一个女人，尤其是一个受到侵害的女人的巨大枷锁。苔丝因所遭受的创伤而抬不起头，因为不够“纯洁”而被爱人遗弃，最终被命运再次推向自己的加害者。这样的命运悲剧怎么能归咎到苔丝身上呢？当苔丝终于奋起反抗、杀死罪人时，这一私刑式的报复却换来了众人的围剿与死刑的惩罚。所谓的道德原则成为了压死苔丝的判决书，这种伪善的道德所带来的系统性的压迫，不仅是苔丝们身上最沉重的镣铐，也是时代的原罪。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;刻画女性友情时，哈代也同样展现了细腻而温柔的笔触。在苔丝和另外三位女伴同时爱上克莱之后，她们的相处并未充满嫉妒与争夺，而是温和、克制又和谐。 至于克莱，他被哈代刻画为“本来有先进的思想、善良的用意，是最近二十五年以来这个时代里出产的典型人物。但虽然他极力想要以独立的见解判断事物，一旦事出非常，他不知不觉地还是信从小的时候所受的训教，还是成见习俗的奴隶。”克莱的挣扎与妥协，正是我们每个人的缩影：我们总以为自己拥有独立的思想，却依然常常不自觉地受制于成见和传统的枷锁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really appreciate Hardy’s delicate yet compassionate portrayal. Tess’s tragedy is a microcosm of a beautiful yet impoverished woman forced to endure the multiple oppressions of family, society, and religion. She was born into a family that is lazy, ambitionless, yet harbors the illusion of changing their fate by marrying off their daughter. In the social context of the 19th century, the burdens of family, the discipline of society, and the harsh judgment of religion all became enormous shackles restraining a woman—especially one who had been violated. Tess is weighed down by the trauma she suffered, abandoned by her lover for not being “pure” enough, and ultimately pushed back into the hands of her perpetrator by fate. How could such a tragic destiny ever be blamed on Tess herself? When she finally rises in resistance and kills her oppressor, her act of vigilante justice is met with public condemnation and the punishment of execution. The so-called moral principles become the verdict that crushes her. This hypocritical morality, bringing systemic oppression, is not only the heaviest chain shackling women like Tess but also the original sin of the era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardy’s delicate and gentle touch is also evident in his portrayal of female friendship. When Tess and her three companions fall in love with Angel, their interactions are not filled with jealousy or rivalry, but rather with restraint, harmony, and mutual understanding. As for Angel, Hardy portrays him as “a man of progressive thought and kind intentions, a typical product of the last twenty-five years. However, though he strives to judge things with independent insight, when faced with extraordinary circumstances, he unconsciously falls back on the teachings of his childhood and remains a slave to conventional prejudices.” Angel’s struggles and compromises are a reflection of us all: we often believe we possess independent thinking, yet unknowingly remain bound by preconceived notions and the chains of tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>书评/ 情人</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lover/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lover/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;相关信息&#34;&gt;相关信息
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;玛格丽特·杜拉斯 (Marguerite Duras )
出版社: 上海译文出版社
译者: 王道乾&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;看过电影再读原著，才能感受到影视化改编对原作的偏离与简化。电影将故事重塑为一段跨越种族与阶级的浪漫爱情，通过精心的镜头语言、音乐配乐和演员表演，将这段关系渲染得富有诗意与美感。两人最终的分离被描绘成命运的无奈，仿佛少女和商人之间是一出爱而不得的爱情悲剧。然而在原著中，杜拉斯笔下的爱情并非少女回忆在越南殖民地生活的重点，甚至都不是她生活中最重要的部分。在种族差异依然巨大的殖民时代，少女和商人之间实质是一场建立在种族上的不平等、社会阶层上的不平等、财富水平上的不平等、文化上的不平等之上的非正常包养关系，而非单纯的爱情故事。电影中营造的浪漫色彩和&amp;quot;禁忌之恋&amp;quot;的错觉，与杜拉斯的创作本意截然不同。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;原著的核心远不止是描述一段跨越种族和社会阶层的爱情，而是聚焦在殖民时代的压迫性结构下，女性在缺乏家庭支持和父爱的环境中对于欲望和感情的自我探索。少女对于家庭的逃离欲望，不仅仅是对爱情的渴望，更是对社会规训和家庭结构压迫的本能反叛。她不仅是这段关系中的被动承受者，更是绝对的主体。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;杜拉斯运用了大量意识流的叙事手法，使得整部作品在时间和空间上呈现出一种迷乱感。她用文字营造历史、情感、家庭和社会构建的多重迷宫。对于任何问题的答案，她都并未提供直接的解释，而是通过人物内心的流动、对时间和空间感知的模糊化，逐层揭示出深层的冲突与欲望。这种独特的叙事风格在电影中未能得到很好的呈现——影片采用更为直白的线性叙事，因此忽略了原著中那种氛围的流动性和情感的复杂性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;电影改编削弱了小说深层的政治、文化和心理层面的探讨——少女在殖民地、家庭和不伦恋情中的探索，是殖民历史中种族歧视、社会结构不平等和失衡家庭伦理作用下的产物，也是对女性在压迫中的挣扎与自我发现的深刻呈现。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after watching the film and then reading the original novel can one appreciate how much the screen adaptation deviates from and simplifies the source material. The film reshapes the story into a romantic love affair transcending race and class, using carefully crafted cinematography, music, and performances to render the relationship poetic and beautiful. The final separation is portrayed as an inevitable twist of fate, as if it were a tragic love story between a young girl and a merchant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the original novel, Duras doesn&amp;rsquo;t focus on the love story as the central point of the girl&amp;rsquo;s memories of colonial Vietnam - it&amp;rsquo;s not even the most important part of her life. In the colonial era when racial differences remained vast, the relationship between the girl and the merchant was essentially an irregular arrangement based on multiple inequalities - racial, social class, wealth, and cultural - rather than a pure love story. The romantic atmosphere and illusion of &amp;lsquo;forbidden love&amp;rsquo; created in the film completely contradicts Duras&amp;rsquo;s original creative intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel&amp;rsquo;s core goes far beyond describing a love affair that crosses racial and social class boundaries. Instead, it focuses on a woman&amp;rsquo;s self-exploration of desire and emotion under colonial oppressive structures, in an environment lacking family support and paternal love. The girl&amp;rsquo;s desire to escape her family isn&amp;rsquo;t merely a yearning for love, but an instinctive rebellion against social discipline and family structural oppression. She isn&amp;rsquo;t just a passive recipient in this relationship, but rather the absolute subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duras employs extensive stream-of-consciousness narrative techniques, creating a sense of disorientation in both time and space throughout the work. She uses words to construct multiple mazes of history, emotion, family, and social construction. Rather than providing direct explanations to any questions, she gradually reveals deeper conflicts and desires through the flow of characters&amp;rsquo; inner thoughts and the blurring of temporal and spatial perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unique narrative style isn&amp;rsquo;t well represented in the film - the movie adopts a more straightforward linear narrative, thus neglecting the fluidity of atmosphere and complexity of emotions present in the original work. The film adaptation weakens the novel&amp;rsquo;s deeper exploration of political, cultural, and psychological aspects - the girl&amp;rsquo;s exploration in the colonial setting, family, and illicit relationship is a product of racial discrimination, social structural inequality, and unbalanced family ethics in colonial history. It&amp;rsquo;s also a profound presentation of women&amp;rsquo;s struggle and self-discovery under oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>书评/ 昨日的世界</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-world-of-yesterday/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-world-of-yesterday/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;斯特凡•茨威格 (Stefan Zweig)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;茨威格笔下的巴黎第一次让我对这座城市心生向往。在他眼中，战前的巴黎（乃至整个欧洲）宛如一座闪耀着理想主义光辉的乌托邦。塞纳河畔，自由的种子破土而出，平等的旗帜在伟人们的呐喊中高高飘扬。那是一个青春永驻的时代：街巷里回荡着欢乐的旋律，屋檐下孕育着无限的可能性。这个巴黎不再只是文学中的象征，而是一座承载人类最纯粹理想的精神花园，每个人都能在自由与平等的晨曦中找到自己的位置。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然而，象征着人类理想的城市终究未能逃脱时代的洪流。从战前的繁荣到两次世界大战后的毁灭，茨威格以亲身经历见证了理想主义的破灭与人性的幽暗。他告诉我们，了解一座城市、一个国家，乃至一个民族，仅仅靠书本与匆匆游览是远远不够的，真正的理解需要与其人民建立深厚的情感联结。个体的命运常常被时代的风暴裹挟，历史的齿轮一次次碾碎美好的希望： 在极权政治的阴影下，理想破灭者服毒自尽，狡诈之徒趁乱攫取荣华，而剩下的芸芸众生在命运长河中随波逐流，苟且偷生。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;整部作品闪耀着深刻的人文关怀，不仅记录了历史，更深刻反思了人类的命运。尽管茨威格的视角是少数的、精英的、幸运的，但他对人性本质的洞察与对和平的呼吁却具有普遍意义 人类文化的建构能否压制内心的原始性，抑或这只是另一个历史循环的起点？ 只是当所有美好的记忆被摧毁、金色的时光化为灰烬时，自我毁灭也未免不是一种保存理想的抗争方式。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zweig&amp;rsquo;s Paris was the first to make me yearn for this city. In his eyes, pre-war Paris (and indeed all of Europe) was like a utopia shining with the light of idealism. Along the Seine, seeds of freedom sprouted, and flags of equality flew high amid the calls of great figures. It was an age of eternal youth: joyful melodies echoed through the streets, and endless possibilities grew under the eaves. This Paris was no longer just a symbol in literature, but a spiritual garden carrying humanity&amp;rsquo;s purest ideals, where everyone could find their place in the dawn of freedom and equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this city symbolizing human ideals could not escape the torrents of time. From pre-war prosperity to destruction after two world wars, Zweig personally witnessed the collapse of idealism and the darkness of human nature. He tells us that understanding a city, a country, or even a nation cannot be achieved merely through books and hasty tours; true understanding requires deep emotional connections with its people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual destinies are often swept up in the storms of their times, with history&amp;rsquo;s gears repeatedly crushing beautiful hopes: under the shadow of totalitarian politics, idealists took their own lives by poison, the cunning seized glory amid chaos, and the remaining masses drifted along the river of fate, barely surviving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire work shines with profound humanistic care, not only recording history but deeply reflecting on human destiny. Although Zweig&amp;rsquo;s perspective was that of a privileged minority elite, his insights into human nature and calls for peace hold universal significance. Can human cultural constructs suppress our primitive inner nature, or is this just the beginning of another historical cycle? Perhaps when all beautiful memories are destroyed and golden times turn to ashes, self-destruction becomes a form of resistance to preserve ideals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>书评/ 暗处的女儿</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lost0daughter/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lost0daughter/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;作者&#34;&gt;作者
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;埃莱娜·费兰特 (Elena Ferrante)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;埃莱娜·费兰特通过一场沙滩上的偶遇，探讨了女性在母职与自我实现之间是否真的可以找到微妙的平衡点。她精准地描绘了母女关系中复杂而深刻的情感纽带——既有深沉的爱，也有难以启齿的恨；既有本能的疼惜，也有隐秘的控制欲；既有无私的奉献，也有难以抑制的嫉妒与竞争。这种情感交织，是任何男性作家都难以真实捕捉的独特体验。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自我的议题贯穿每个人生命始终，但与母亲的关系何尝不是同样难以逃离的命题？作品中的主人公面临着一个永恒的困境：在传统母职期待与个人自我实现之间，是否真的只能二选一？ 那些因自我意识强烈而逃离家庭的母亲究竟是懦弱，还是在进行勇敢的抗争？ 传统母职叙事用罗网将母亲塑造成无私奉献的圣人，仿佛在成为母亲的那一刻，就必须与过往的不成熟彻底切割，可是她们真的准备好了吗？ 母亲首先是人，是有自我意识和个人渴望的完整个体，而不是某种被理想化的工具。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;费兰特的笔触如同一把手术刀，细腻而精准地剖开了母亲的心理世界，揭示了母女之间那种既紧密相连又暗藏裂隙的关系。剖开后流出的，是血、是眼泪，是黑水、是周而复始的回响、是潜藏的渴望、不甘与无法言说的阴暗。母爱背面是挣扎、失落和渴望，而暗处的女儿们，则在母亲的阴影中成长，继承着她们的特质，在生命的长河中延续着这场永恒的循环。 她们或重复，或抗拒，或超越母亲的命运，但无论如何，但母女之间深刻的情感纽带始终像一根无形的丝线，将她们的生命编织在一起。这种深沉而复杂的联结，既是负累，也是力量。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a chance encounter on the beach, Elena Ferrante explores whether women can truly find a delicate balance between motherhood and self-realization. She precisely portrays the complex and profound emotional bonds in mother-daughter relationships - deep love alongside unspoken hatred; instinctive tenderness with hidden desires for control; selfless devotion mixed with uncontrollable jealousy and competition. This emotional interweaving represents a unique experience that male writers find difficult to capture authentically.
The question of self runs throughout everyone’s life, but isn’t the relationship with one’s mother equally inescapable? The protagonist faces an eternal dilemma: between traditional maternal expectations and personal self-realization, must it really be an either-or choice? Are mothers who flee their families due to strong self-awareness cowardly, or are they engaging in brave resistance? Traditional maternal narratives cast mothers as selfless saints with their web of expectations, as if the moment of becoming a mother requires a complete break from past immaturity - but are they truly ready?
A mother is first and foremost a human being, a complete individual with self-awareness and personal desires, not some idealized tool. Ferrante’s writing is like a surgical knife, delicately and precisely cutting open the psychological world of mothers, revealing the relationship between mothers and daughters that is both intimately connected yet harboring cracks. What flows out after the incision is blood, tears, dark water, recurring echoes, hidden desires, resentment, and unspeakable darkness.
Behind maternal love lies struggle, loss, and yearning, while in the shadows, daughters grow in their mothers’ shade, inheriting their characteristics, perpetuating this eternal cycle in the river of life. They may repeat, resist, or transcend their mothers’ fate, but regardless, the profound emotional bond between mother and daughter remains like an invisible thread, weaving their lives together. This deep and complex connection is both a burden and a source of strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
