<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>中国 on 演示站点</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/zh-cn/categories/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD/</link>
        <description>Recent content in 中国 on 演示站点</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>zh-cn</language>
        <copyright>Example Person</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1sle29.github.io/zh-cn/categories/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>我的母亲做保洁 - 书评</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/zh-cn/p/test-chinese/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/zh-cn/p/test-chinese/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;我的母亲做保洁---书评&#34;&gt;我的母亲做保洁 - 书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;开年第一本想读个轻松的非虚构纪实文学，结果也不是很轻松。作者作为女儿，书写在深圳务工的妈妈和妈妈们的故事，她们是清洁工、保姆、小商贩，维修工，她们无处不在，但她们的声音和存在却常常被忽略。这些妈妈们本该在退休年龄安享晚年，却为了子女（尤其是为了托举儿子）的未来背井离乡，从事着缺乏劳动保障的工作。客观来说，这本书作为2024年豆瓣榜单图书，名过其实了，但真诚的书写确实打动人心。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在记录妈妈的人生时，重新思考一座城市的运转：为什么最不可或缺、造福最多人的工作，在社会上往往得到最少的回报？苦难的生活不该被歌颂，但看到被忽略群体的挣扎与努力很重要，以及思考我们能做些什么？除了在日常生活中给予底层服务业者应有的尊重、有意识地在使用公共设施时减少污染和损耗外，更应关注劳动法规的完善，让这些劳动者获得应有的权益保障和劳动尊严。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-monther-is-a-cleaning-lady--thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;My Monther is a cleaning lady / Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my first book of the year, I wanted to read something light and chose this non-fiction narrative, but it turned out not to be so light after all. The author, writing as a daughter, tells the stories of her mother and other mothers who work in Shenzhen. They are cleaners, housekeepers, small vendors, and maintenance workers - they are everywhere, yet their voices and existence are often ignored.These mothers should be enjoying their retirement years, but instead, they leave their hometowns to work in jobs with little labor protection, all for their children&amp;rsquo;s future (especially their sons). Objectively speaking, this book, as one of Douban&amp;rsquo;s best books of 2024, , is somewhat overrated, but its sincere writing truly touches the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While documenting her mother&amp;rsquo;s life, the author makes us rethink how a city functions: why do the most essential jobs that benefit the most people often receive the least reward in society? While we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t glorify hardship, it&amp;rsquo;s important to see the struggles and efforts of these overlooked groups and think about what we can do. Beyond showing proper respect to service workers in daily life and consciously reducing pollution and waste when using public facilities, we should pay more attention to improving labor laws, ensuring these workers receive proper rights protection and dignity in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
