<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>法国 on 1sle</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E6%B3%95%E5%9B%BD/</link>
        <description>Recent content in 法国 on 1sle</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>1sle</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1sle29.github.io/categories/%E6%B3%95%E5%9B%BD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>书评/ 情人</title>
        <link>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lover/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://1sle29.github.io/p/the-lover/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;相关信息&#34;&gt;相关信息
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;玛格丽特·杜拉斯 (Marguerite Duras )
出版社: 上海译文出版社
译者: 王道乾&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;书评&#34;&gt;书评
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;看过电影再读原著，才能感受到影视化改编对原作的偏离与简化。电影将故事重塑为一段跨越种族与阶级的浪漫爱情，通过精心的镜头语言、音乐配乐和演员表演，将这段关系渲染得富有诗意与美感。两人最终的分离被描绘成命运的无奈，仿佛少女和商人之间是一出爱而不得的爱情悲剧。然而在原著中，杜拉斯笔下的爱情并非少女回忆在越南殖民地生活的重点，甚至都不是她生活中最重要的部分。在种族差异依然巨大的殖民时代，少女和商人之间实质是一场建立在种族上的不平等、社会阶层上的不平等、财富水平上的不平等、文化上的不平等之上的非正常包养关系，而非单纯的爱情故事。电影中营造的浪漫色彩和&amp;quot;禁忌之恋&amp;quot;的错觉，与杜拉斯的创作本意截然不同。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;原著的核心远不止是描述一段跨越种族和社会阶层的爱情，而是聚焦在殖民时代的压迫性结构下，女性在缺乏家庭支持和父爱的环境中对于欲望和感情的自我探索。少女对于家庭的逃离欲望，不仅仅是对爱情的渴望，更是对社会规训和家庭结构压迫的本能反叛。她不仅是这段关系中的被动承受者，更是绝对的主体。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;杜拉斯运用了大量意识流的叙事手法，使得整部作品在时间和空间上呈现出一种迷乱感。她用文字营造历史、情感、家庭和社会构建的多重迷宫。对于任何问题的答案，她都并未提供直接的解释，而是通过人物内心的流动、对时间和空间感知的模糊化，逐层揭示出深层的冲突与欲望。这种独特的叙事风格在电影中未能得到很好的呈现——影片采用更为直白的线性叙事，因此忽略了原著中那种氛围的流动性和情感的复杂性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;电影改编削弱了小说深层的政治、文化和心理层面的探讨——少女在殖民地、家庭和不伦恋情中的探索，是殖民历史中种族歧视、社会结构不平等和失衡家庭伦理作用下的产物，也是对女性在压迫中的挣扎与自我发现的深刻呈现。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-after-reading&#34;&gt;Thoughts after reading
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after watching the film and then reading the original novel can one appreciate how much the screen adaptation deviates from and simplifies the source material. The film reshapes the story into a romantic love affair transcending race and class, using carefully crafted cinematography, music, and performances to render the relationship poetic and beautiful. The final separation is portrayed as an inevitable twist of fate, as if it were a tragic love story between a young girl and a merchant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the original novel, Duras doesn&amp;rsquo;t focus on the love story as the central point of the girl&amp;rsquo;s memories of colonial Vietnam - it&amp;rsquo;s not even the most important part of her life. In the colonial era when racial differences remained vast, the relationship between the girl and the merchant was essentially an irregular arrangement based on multiple inequalities - racial, social class, wealth, and cultural - rather than a pure love story. The romantic atmosphere and illusion of &amp;lsquo;forbidden love&amp;rsquo; created in the film completely contradicts Duras&amp;rsquo;s original creative intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel&amp;rsquo;s core goes far beyond describing a love affair that crosses racial and social class boundaries. Instead, it focuses on a woman&amp;rsquo;s self-exploration of desire and emotion under colonial oppressive structures, in an environment lacking family support and paternal love. The girl&amp;rsquo;s desire to escape her family isn&amp;rsquo;t merely a yearning for love, but an instinctive rebellion against social discipline and family structural oppression. She isn&amp;rsquo;t just a passive recipient in this relationship, but rather the absolute subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duras employs extensive stream-of-consciousness narrative techniques, creating a sense of disorientation in both time and space throughout the work. She uses words to construct multiple mazes of history, emotion, family, and social construction. Rather than providing direct explanations to any questions, she gradually reveals deeper conflicts and desires through the flow of characters&amp;rsquo; inner thoughts and the blurring of temporal and spatial perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unique narrative style isn&amp;rsquo;t well represented in the film - the movie adopts a more straightforward linear narrative, thus neglecting the fluidity of atmosphere and complexity of emotions present in the original work. The film adaptation weakens the novel&amp;rsquo;s deeper exploration of political, cultural, and psychological aspects - the girl&amp;rsquo;s exploration in the colonial setting, family, and illicit relationship is a product of racial discrimination, social structural inequality, and unbalanced family ethics in colonial history. It&amp;rsquo;s also a profound presentation of women&amp;rsquo;s struggle and self-discovery under oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;推荐指数&#34;&gt;推荐指数
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;⭐⭐⭐⭐&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
